A Guide to the Records of the Secretary of Veterans Affairs and Homeland Security, 2005-2012, (bulk 2010-2011)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Secretary of Veterans Affairs and Homeland Security, 2005-2012, (bulk 2010-2011)
The Library of Virginia
51438
2 cu. ft. (2 boxes)
Virginia. Office of the Secretary of Veterans Affairs and Homeland Security
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from Suzanne Trachy, Office of Veterans Affairs and Homeland Security on 9 January 2014.
Biographical/Historical Information
In 2010 Governor Robert F. McDonnell initiated legislative action which changed and re-organized the former Office of Commonwealth Preparedness (OCP) into the Office of Veterans Affairs and Homeland Security (OVAHS). With this legislation the Department of Veterans Services (DVS) was moved from the Office of Public Safety to the Office of Veterans Affairs and Homeland Security along with the Virginia War Memorial. In April of 2011 Terrie L. Suit was appointed by Governor McDonnell to the position of Secretary of Veterans Affairs and Homeland Security after previously serving as Assistant to the Governor for Commonwealth Preparedness. James W. Hopper was appointed Deputy Secretary. She stepped down from the position on September 22nd, 2013 after being selected as the Chief Executive Office of the Virginia Association of REALTORS (VAR). Hopper, a previous staff member of McDonnell's tenure as Attorney General from 2006-2009 took over the Secretary's position until January 2014.
The Office of Commonwealth Preparedness had originated from Governor James Gilmore's Virginia Preparedness and Security Panel created after the September 11th terrorist attacks to better prevent and respond to such attacks in Virginia. Shortly thereafter, Governor-elect Mark R. Warner named John H. Hager to the newly created position of assistant to the governor for commonwealth preparedness, now a cabinet-level position, on 28 December 2001. Hager served as lieutenant governor under Governor James Gilmore and was a member of the Virginia Preparedness and Security Panel. On 31 January 2002, Governor Warner issued Executive Order 7, also known as the Secure Virginia Initiative, which rescinded Gilmore's Virginia Preparedness and Security Panel. Executive Order 7 also created the Secure Virginia Panel to review, evaluate, and make recommendations relating to emergency preparedness for the Commonwealth. The Secure Virginia Panel, which became the Secure Commonwealth Panel under Executive Order 69, was to consist of twenty members, later increased to twenty-eight members, under the Assistant to the Governor for Commonwealth Preparedness as chairman. The Office of Commonwealth Preparedness and the Secure Commonwealth Panel were later codified under 2.2-304 through 2.2-306 of the Code of Virginia.
The Office of Commonwealth Preparedness was created with the purpose of developing a coordinated security and preparedness strategy and implementation plan. The Assistant to the Governor for Commonwealth Preparedness, who is appointed by the governor for a term of four years, is responsible for the general management of the Office. The Secretary of Veterans Affairs and Homeland Security, was later renamed Secretary of Veterans and Defense Affairs by Governor Terry McAuliffe in 2014, with Homeland Security transferred to the Secretary of Public Safety, (renamed Secretary of Public Safety and Homeland Security).
Scope and Content
The Secretary of Veterans Affairs and Homeland Security records consist of two boxes divided into fourteen series. Series are listed below and they reflect the names and the defined grouping records upon arrival to the archives at the Library of Virginia. These records document the work of Secretary Terrie L. Suit and the Office of Veterans Affairs and Homeland Security during Governor Robert F. McDonnell's gubernatorial term. The bulk of the records can relate to base closings, campus security, hurricane preparedness, interoperability, the National Capital Region, and various office projects.
Some of the key initiatives, advisory boards, and task forces during Suit's tenure included the standardization of emergency radio communication, critical infrastructure protection, commonwealth interoperability and preparedness against terrorist attacks, and campus preparedness. Included among the various types of records are agendas, correspondence, minutes, newsletters, memoranda, programs, reports, and surveys. Researchers should search across series as some issues, offices, and subjects are cross referenced or exist in various series.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Administration
Series II: Boards, Commissions, and Groups
Series III: Department of Homeland Security
Series IV: Department of Homeland Security Grants
Series V: Department of Veterans Services
Series VI: Housing Issues
Series VII: Hurricane Preparedness
Series VIII: Initiatives
Series IX: National Capital Region
Series X: National Governors Association
Series XI: Military Installations
Series XII: Military Issues
Series XIII: Military Relations
Series XIV: Stakeholders
Related Material
The Governor Robert F. McDonnell Administration Web Archive Collection, 2010-2014 contains archived versions of websites for the Governor's Office, his initiative sites, and the sites of his cabinet secretaries, including the Secretary of Veterans Affairs and Homeland Security and Secretary of Public Safety.
The Records of the Virginia Secretary of Public Safety Collection includes material from the office during Gov. Robert F. McDonnell's tenure.
The Records of Governor Robert F. McDonnell's Secretary of Transportation Collection
The Records of Governor Robert F. McDonnell's Secretary of Administration Collection
Contents List
- Series I: Administration
  - Cabinet 2011 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Father Creedon/VOICE 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Future's Work group 2011 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Governor's Emergency Duties 2010 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Governor's Speech to Senate Finance 2011 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Legislation 2011 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Material-Support/Research 2005-2011 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Office Coin 2010 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - OAG Opinions 2010 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Secure Commonwealth Strategic Plan 2010 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Terrie L. Suit 2009 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Transition Information (1 of 3) 2009-2010 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Transition Information (2 of 3) 2009-2010 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Transition Information (3 of 3) 2009-2010 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Virginia Threat Picture 2011 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Virginia War Memorial 2011 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series II: Boards, Commissions, and Groups
  - Board of Veterans Services 2010 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Council of Governors (1 of 2) 2010 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Council of Governors (2 of 2) 2010 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Fort Monroe (FMA) Background (1 of 2) 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Fort Monroe (FMA) Background (2 of 2) 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Northern Virginia Emergency Response System (NVERS)(1 of 2) 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Northern Virginia Emergency Response System (NVERS)(2 of 2) 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Interagency Economic Development Working Group 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Oceana/Fentress Advisory Group 2010 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Secure Commonwealth Panel 2010 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - State, Local, Tribal, and Private Sector Advisory Committee (SLTPS-PAC) 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Virginia National Defense Industrial Authority (VNDIA) 2010 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Virginia Area Maritime Security Committee (1 of 2) 2008-2010 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Veterans Services Foundation 2010 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Virginia Military Advisory Council 2010 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Series III: Department of Homeland Security
  - DHS Security Clearance Process 2010 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - National Critical Infrastructure Prioritization (CIP) Program 2010 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Office of Intelligence and Analysis 2010 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Local, State, Tribal, and Federal (LSTF) Preparedness Task Force 2010 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Protective Security Advisors Info 2009-2010 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - REAL ID 2010 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Regional Catastrophic Preparedness Team 2008-2010 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Senior Official Exercise 2010 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Transportation Security Administration- Visible Intermodal Prevention and Response (TSA-VIPR) 2010 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Series IV: Department of Homeland Security Grants
  - Grant information (1 of 3) 2008-2012 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Grant information (2 of 3) 2008-2012 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Grant information (3 of 3) 2008-2012 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Series V: Department of Veterans Services
  - Department of Veterans Services (DVS) - General 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Homeless Vets 2011 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Virginia Veterans Care Center 2011 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Series VI: Housing Issues
  - Buffer Zone Protection Program 2011 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Chinese Drywall 2010 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Virginia Foreclosure Taskforce (1 of 4) 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Virginia Foreclosure Taskforce (2 of 4) 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Virginia Foreclosure Taskforce (3 of 4) 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Virginia Foreclosure Taskforce (4 of 4) 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Series VII: Hurricane Preparedness
  - Elected Official's Guide to Emergencies and Disasters 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Hampton Roads 2010-2012 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Hurricane Preparedness Reports 2008-2010 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - HR Chief Administrative Officers (CAO) Tabletop Exercise 2010 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Shelter in Place 2010 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - William and Mary Sheltering 2011 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Series VIII: Initiatives
  - Agro Terrorism 2011 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Cardinal Horizon 2011 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Critical Infrastructure Urban Training Facility 2011 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Joint Commission on Transportation Accountability 2011 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Military Strategic Response Fund 2010 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Radio - D Block 2011 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Radio - COMLINC 2011 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Radio - STARS 2010 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series IX: National Capital Region
  - Emergency Preparedness Council (1 of 2) 2009-2010 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Emergency Preparedness Council (2 of 2) 2009-2010 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - NCR/DHS Briefing 2011 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - NCR Correspondence 2010-2011 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - NCR Grant Information (1 of 2) 2010-2011 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - NCR Grant Information (2 of 2) 2010-2011 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Northern Virginia Evacuation Plan 2009 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Northern Virginia Evacuation Plan 2009 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Senior Policy Group (SPG) - Council of Governments (COG) Duties ca. 2010 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Strategic Plan 2010 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Urban Area Security Initiative 2011 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Series X: National Governors Association
  - Governors Homeland Security Advisors Council (GHSAC) 2010 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Homeland Security Guides (1 of 2) 2010 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Homeland Security Guides (2 of 2) 2010 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Series XI: Military Installations
  - Dahlgreen 2009-2011 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - For A.P. Hill 2010 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Fort Belvoir (1 of 2) 2009-2010 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Fort Belvoir (2 of 2) 2009-2010 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Fort Eustis 2011 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Fort Lee 2009-2010 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Fort Monroe 2010 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Fusion Centers 2010 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Joint Forces Command (JFCOM) 2010 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Langley Air Force Base 2011 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Marine Corps Base - Quantico 2011 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - National Capital Region (NCR)/Military District of Washington (MDW)Headquarters 2010 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Norfolk Naval Shipyard 2010 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Oceana (1 of 2) 2005-2011 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Oceana (2 of 2) 2005-2011 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Series XII: Military Issues
  - Base Realignment and Closure (BRAC) 2010-2011 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Child care 2009-2011 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Department of Defense (DoD) Oil Drilling 2012 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Series XIII: Military Relations
  - Boy Scout Jamboree 2011 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Carrier 2010 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Hampton - City 2010 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Hampton Roads 2010 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Miscellaneous 2010-2011 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Office of Economic Adjustment (OEA) - Grants 2006-2011 (Box 2, Folder 48)
- Series XIV: Stakeholders
  - Northern Virginia Fire Chiefs 2010 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Virginia Voluntary Organizations Active in Disaster (VOAD) 2010 (Box 2, Folder 50)